Here are some images of clusters of galaxies.
هذه بعض الصّور لعناقيد مجرّات.
They're exactly what they sound like.
وهي فعلا اسم على مسمّى،
They are these huge collections of galaxies,
إنّها مجموعات كبيرة من المجرات
bound together by their mutual gravity.
مرتبطة معا عبر قوى الجاذبية بينها.
So most of the points that you see on the screen
معظم النّقاط التي ترونها على الشاشة
are not individual stars,
ليست نجوما فردية،
but collections of stars, or galaxies.
لكن مجموعة من النّجوم أو المجرات.
Now, by showing you some of these images,
الآن، من خلال مشاركة بعض هذه الصور معكم،
I hope that you will quickly see that
أرجو أنّ تتفطّنوا إلى أنّ
galaxy clusters are these beautiful objects,
عناقيد المجرات هي في غاية الجمال
but more than that,
لكن، أكثر من ذلك،
I think galaxy clusters are mysterious,
أظنّ أنّها أمر غامض
they are surprising,
يثير الدّهشة
and they're useful.
وهي أيضا مفيدة.
Useful as the universe's most massive laboratories.
مفيدة بكونها أكبر مختبرات الكون.
And as laboratories, to describe galaxy clusters
وكمختبرات، فإن وصف عناقيد المجرات يعني
is to describe the experiments
وصف التّجارب التي يمكنك
that you can do with them.
إجراؤها بواسطة هذه العناقيد.
And I think there are four major types,
وأظنّ أنّ هناك أربعة أنواع رئيسية،
and the first type that I want to describe
أوّل نوع أرغب في وصفه
is probing the very big.
سبر ما هو كبير جداً.
So, how big?
كبير إلى أيّ درجة؟
Well, here is an image of a particular galaxy cluster.
حسنا، هذه صورة لعنقود مجرات معيّن.
It is so massive that the light passing through it
إنّه كبير جدّا لدرجة أنّ الضوء المارّ عبره
is being bent, it's being distorted
يتقوّس، ينحرف عن المسار المستقيم
by the extreme gravity of this cluster.
تحت تأثير الجاذبية الهائلة لهذا العنقود.
And, in fact, if you look very carefully
وفي الواقع، لو نظرتم جيدا بانتباه
you'll be able to see rings around this cluster.
سوف تتمكّنون من رؤية حلقات حول هذا العنقود.
Now, to give you a number,
لإعطائكم رقما،
this particular galaxy cluster
فإنّ هذا العنقود المجريّ
has a mass of over one million billion suns.
ذو كتلة تساوي مليون مليار شمس.
It's just mind-boggling how massive these systems can get.
كبر هذه الأنظمة يترك عقولنا مذهولة.
But more than their mass,
لكن، فضلا عن كتلتها،
they have this additional feature.
فهي ذات خاصية أخرى.
They are essentially isolated systems,
إنّها بالأساس أنظمة منعزلة،
so if we like, we can think of them
لذا يمكننا التّفكير فيها
as a scaled-down version of the entire universe.
كأنّها نسخة مصغّرة من الكون كلّه.
And many of the questions that we might have
والعديد من الأسئلة التي قد تخطر بأذهاننا
about the universe at large scales,
حول الكون الكبير
such as, how does gravity work?
مثل، كيف تعمل الجاذبية؟
might be answered by studying these systems.
يمكن الإجابة عنها من خلال دراسة هذه الأنظمة.
So that was very big.
كان ذلك الكبر الشديد.
The second things is very hot.
الأمر الثاني هو شدة الحرارة.
Okay, if I take an image of a galaxy cluster,
حسنا، إن أخذت صورة لعنقود مجريّ،
and I subtract away all of the starlight,
وقمت بحذف كلّ الضوء الصادر عن النّجوم،
what I'm left with is this big, blue blob.
سيتبقّى أمامي نقطة زرقاء كبيرة.
This is in false color.
هذا ليس اللّون الحقيقيّ.
It's actually X-ray light that we're seeing.
إنّ ما نراه هو في الواقع ضوء أشعة اكس.
And the question is, if it's not galaxies,
والسؤال الذي يطرح هو، إن لم يكن ذلك صادرا عن المجرات،
what is emitting this light?
فما هو مصدر هذا الضّوء؟
The answer is hot gas,
الجواب هو: الغاز الحارّ،
million-degree gas --
ذو مليون درجة --
in fact, it's plasma.
في الواقع، إنّه البلازما.
And the reason why it's so hot
والسبب وراء شدة سخونته،
goes back to the previous slide.
ذو علاقة بالصّور السابقة.
The extreme gravity of these systems
الجاذبية الهائلة لهذه الأنظمة
is accelerating particles of gas to great speeds,
تقوم بتسريع جسيمات الغاز إلى سرعة كبيرة
and great speeds means great temperatures.
التي تعني درجات حرارة عالية جدا.
So this is the main idea,
إذن تلك هي الفكرة العامة،
but science is a rough draft.
لكن العلم أصعب من ذلك.
There are many basic properties about this plasma
هناك العديد من الخصائص الأساسية للبلازما
that still confuse us,
والتي لا تزال تربكنا،
still puzzle us,
وتثير دهشتنا
and still push our understanding
وتدفع بفهمنا
of the physics of the very hot.
لفيزياء ما هو حارّ جدا.
Third thing: probing the very small.
الأمر الثالث: سبر ما هو صغير جداً
Now, to explain this, I need to tell you
لتفسير ذلك، أحتاج أن أخبركم
a very disturbing fact.
بحقيقة مدهشة.
Most of the universe's matter
معظم المادة في الكون
is not made up of atoms.
ليست متكونة من الذرات.
You were lied to.
لقد كذبوا عليك.
Most of it is made up of something very, very mysterious,
معظمها متكوّن من شيء في غاية الغموض
which we call dark matter.
نسمّيه "المادة المظلمة".
Dark matter is something that doesn't like to interact very much,
المادة المظلمة هي أمر لا يحبّذ التّفاعل كثيرا،
except through gravity,
إلاّ من خلال الجاذبية،
and of course we would like to learn more about it.
وبالطبع نحن نرغب في معرفة المزيد عنها.
If you're a particle physicist,
إنّ كنت فيزيائيّ جسيمات،
you want to know what happens when we smash things together.
فسترغب في معرفة ما الذي يحدث عند اصطدام الأشياء ببعضها.
And dark matter is no exception.
والمادة المظلمة ليس باستثناء.
Well, how do we do this?
حسنا، كيف نقوم بذلك؟
To answer that question,
للإجابة،
I'm going to have to ask another one,
سأطرح سؤالا أخر،
which is, what happens when galaxy clusters collide?
وهو، ما الذي يحدث عند اصطدام عناقيد المجرات ببعضها؟
Here is an image.
هذه صورة.
Since galaxy clusters are representative
بما أنّ عناقيد المجرات هي صور تمثيلية
slices of the universe, scaled-down versions.
مصغّرة عن الكون
They are mostly made up of dark matter,
إنّها متكوّنة في معظمها من المادة المظلمة
and that's what you see in this bluish purple.
وهو ما ترونه باللّون البنفسجي المائل للزرقة.
The red represents the hot gas,
الأحمر يرمز للغاز الحار،
and, of course, you can see many galaxies.
وبالطبع يمكنكم رؤية عديد المجرات.
What's happened is a particle accelerator
ما حدث هو تعجيل جسيميّ
at a huge, huge scale.
على مقياس كبير جدّا.
And this is very important,
وهذا هامّ جدا،
because what it means is that very, very small
لأنّه يعني أنّ تلك التّأثيرات
effects that might be difficult to detect in the lab,
الصغيرة جدا التي قد يصعب ضبطها في المختبر،
might be compounded and compounded
يمكن أن يكون مركّبا ومركّبا
into something that we could possibly observe in nature.
إلى أمر قد يكون بإمكاننا مراقبته في الطبيعة
So, it's very funny.
الأمر مضحك جدّا.
The reason why galaxy clusters
السبب وراء كون عناقيد المجرات
can teach us about dark matter,
قادرة على تعليمنا حول المادة المظلمة،
the reason why galaxy clusters
والسبب وراء كونها قادرة
can teach us about the physics of the very small,
على تعليمنا حول فيزياء الجسيمات،
is precisely because they are so very big.
هو أنّها في غاية الضخامة.
Fourth thing: the physics of the very strange.
الأمر الرابع: فيزياء الأمور الغريبة جدّا.
Certainly what I've said so far is crazy.
ما قلته يبدو فعلا ضربا من الجنون.
Okay, if there's anything stranger
إن كان هناك أمر ما غريب
I think it has to be dark energy.
فأنا أعتقد أنّه سيكون الطاقة المظلمة.
If I throw a ball into the air,
إن قمت برمي كرة في الهواء،
I expect it to go up.
أتوقّع منها أن تتجّه نحو الأعلى.
What I don't expect is that it go up
ما لا أتوٌّقعه هو أن تتجّه نحو الأعلى
at an ever-increasing rate.
بسرعة متسارعة.
Similarly, cosmologists understand why
تماما، فإنّ علماء الكونيات يفهمون سبب
the universe is expanding.
توسّع الكون.
They don't understand why it's expanding
ما لا يفهمونه هو سبب توسّعه
at an ever-increasing rate.
بنسق متسارع.
They give the cause of this
لقد أطلقوا على سبب هذا
accelerated expansion a name,
التّوسع المتسارع إسما،
and they call it dark energy.
وهو: الطاقة المظلمة.
And, again, we want to learn more about it.
و مجدّدا، نحن نرغب في تعلّم المزيد عن الأمر.
So, one particular question that we have is,
هناك سؤال محدّد يخطر بأذهاننا وهو
how does dark energy affect the universe
كيف تؤثّر الطاقة المظلمة في الكون
at the largest scales?
على مستويات كبيرة؟
Depending on how strong it is,
استنادا على مدى قوّتها،
maybe structure forms faster or slower.
ربّما تتشكّل الأشكال أسرع أو أبطأ.
Well, the problem with the large-scale structure
مشكلة الهياكل الكبيرة الحجم الموجودة
of the universe is that it's horribly complicated.
بالكون هي أنّها في غاية التّعقيد.
Here is a computer simulation.
هذه محاكاة كمبيوتر.
And we need a way to simplify it.
ونحن نحتاج لطريقة لتبسيطها.
Well, I like to think about this using an analogy.
أحبّ استعمال الأمر كتشبيه.
If I want to understand the sinking of the Titanic,
إن رغبت في فهم طريقة غرق التيتانيك،
the most important thing to do
فإنّ أهم شيء يجب فعله هو
is not to model the little positions
عدم تصميم الوضعيات الصغيرة
of every single little piece of the boat that broke off.
لكلّ جزء صغير تحطّم من السفينة.
The most important thing to do is
أهمّ ما يجب فعله هو
to track the two biggest parts.
متابعة الأجزاء الكبيرة.
Similarly, I can learn a lot about the universe
بنفس الطريقة، يمكننا التعلّم عن الكون
at the largest scales
بمقاييسه الكبيرة
by tracking its biggest pieces
من خلال متابعة أضخم الأجزاء فيه
and those biggest pieces are clusters of galaxies.
التي هي عناقيد المجرات.
So, as I come to a close,
إذن، اقتربت من الانتهاء،
you might feel slightly cheated.
قد تحسّ بأنّه تمّ غشّك.
I mean, I began by talking about
أقصد أنّني بدأت المحادثة بالحديث عن
how galaxy clusters are useful,
كيف أنّ عناقيد المجرات مفيدة
and I've given some reasons,
وأعطيت بعض الأدلة على ذلك،
but what is their use really?
لكن ما هي فائدتها الأصلية؟
Well, to answer this,
للإجابة على ذلك،
I want to give you a quote by Henry Ford
أرغب في اعطائكم اقتباسا عن هنري فورد
when he was asked about cars.
عندما طرح عليه سؤال عن السيارات.
He had this to say:
لقد قال الآتي:
"If I had asked people what they wanted,
"إن قمت بسؤال النّاس عمّا يريدونه،
they would have said faster horses."
لقالوا: أحصنة أسرع."
Today, we as a society are faced
اليوم، نحن كمجتمع نجد أنفسنا في مواجهة
with many, many difficult problems.
العديد من المشاكل.
And the solutions to these problems are not obvious.
و الحلول لهذه المشاكل ليست واضحة.
They are not faster horses.
إنّها ليست الأحصنة السريعة.
They will require an enormous amount of
بل يحتاج الأمر كمية كبيرة من
scientific ingenuity.
الإبداع العلمي.
So, yes, we need to focus,
لذلك فعلينا أن نركّز،
yes, we need to concentrate,
نعم نحتاج للتركيز،
but we also need to remember that
لكننا أيضا نحتاج للتذّكر
innovation, ingenuity, inspiration --
أنّ الاختراع والإبداع والإلهام
these things come
كلّها تأتي
when we broaden our field of vision
عندما نضيّق أفق رؤيتنا
when we step back
وعند العودة إلى الوراء
when we zoom out.
ونظر للصورة الأكبر.
And I can't think of a better way to do this than
لا أستطيع التفكير في طريقة أفضل للقيام بذلك
by studying the universe around us. Thanks.
إلاّ من خلال دراسة الكون من حولنا. شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)